黑客你们好
hello hackers
欢迎回到pwn college
welcome back to pwn College
我们在这个视频中讨论的是
we're talking in this video about
静态分析逆向工具
static reverse engineering tools
作为逆向工程模块的一部分
as part of our reverse engineering module
让我们开始吧
let's roll
什么是静态工具? 静态工具是
what are static tools well static tools are
一个术语
a term
意思是
meaning
这种工具用来分析在磁盘上的程序文件
the analysis tools were created for analyzing a program at rest
而不是内存中的程序进程
not while it's running this is
这与我们之后会讲到的动态工具相反
in opposition to dynamic tooling which we'll talk about later
静态工具只查看Elf文件中的内容
static tools just look at what is in the Elf file
不需要查看程序跑起来后会做什么
not necessarily what the file does when it's you know trying to get its work done
让我们从一些简单易学的工具开始
let's start with some simple (to) learn type tools
首先
first of all
我们已经在elf基础课上看过kaitai struct
we've already looked at kaitai struct in the Elf Fundamentals lecture
如果你还不熟悉这个工具
if you aren't familiar with this tool yet
回去看看，这是一个在浏览器中运行的很酷的工具
go back and watch it it's a pretty cool tool runs in your browser
从这个链接，你可以上传ELF文件，zip文件
from this link and you can upload ELF files but also zip files
各种不同格式的pdf文件
all sorts of different formats Pdfs
它能让你探索文件的不同部分
and it'll let you kind of explore the different pieces of it of the file
界面很酷
with a cool interface
我们在之前的课程中见过nm
we've seen previously in the course nm
它列出了ELF文件的导入和导出符号
it lists out the symbols imported and exported by a file
如果你在程序中使用了printf
so if you use printf you can use in your executable
你可以用nm看到printf就在那里
you can use nm to see you know that printf is there
这是这是一个快速的
it's it's a a quick um
快速的方法来感受一下
quick way to just kind of get a feel for what
程序可能会做什么
the program might do
strings会打印
strings dumps a bunch of ASCII strings
在文件中它能找到的任何ASCII字符串
searches through the file for any ASCII strings it can find
以及其他格式字符串，如果你配置不同的参数
and other formats if you configure it differently
这对理解从哪里开始逆向任务非常有用
can be very useful actually in understanding where to start in your reversing quest
Objdump一个简单好用的反汇编程序
objdump nice simpler a simple disassembler
你们在其他视频中见过我用过
you've seen me use it in other videos
但是我们将在这个模块中使用更重量级的东西
but we are going to use something more heavyweight in this module and
我会快速地展示一下checksec
checksec I'm gonna show Checksec real quick
Checksec能分析可执行文件所使用的安全特性
Checksec analyzes the security features that are used by an executable
最好在尝试利用它的漏洞之前用它分析一下
this is very nice to do before trying to exploit it
在这个模块中，我们不会做漏洞利用
we won't be exploiting anything in this module
但我会给你们展示一下这个工具
but I'll show it to you
算是个预习吧
kind of as a as a preview
在这里我编译了我的shellcode.elf
here I compiled my shellcode.Elf
这是上个视频的例子
this is the example from a last video that was
基本上是一个cat
basically a cat program that was
我用汇编写的
that I wrote in Assembly
我应该重命名这个shellcode.s 成cat.s
I should actually rename this shellcode.s  to cat.s
这样就好了
that would be good okay
这是我的cat.elf, 好
okay here's my cat.elf  awesome
如果我checksec
if I checksec
哦
oops
如果我checksec
if I checksec
cat.elf
它
it
我去
oh my god
终于好了
boom finally okay
它向我展示了这个文件的一系列不同的安全属性
it shows me a bunch of different security properties of this file
在那里
there
文件导入了12个符号，我可以使用nm
the file has 12 symbols that it imports I can use nm
去弄清楚
to uh figure that out
这只是部分
that's just the sections
对不起
sorry
nm -D
nm dash d
嗯
um
nm -a
nm dash a
只有11个符号，我也不知道另一个去哪了
11 symbols I don't know where the other one it went
好了
there you go
不管怎样
anyways
这些都是有用的简单工具，我们现在真正的目标是
these are useful simple tools but really what we're here for is
重量级的——高级反汇编器，对吧
the heavyweight stuff the advanced disassemblers right
逆向工程是一个很热门的话题
so reverse engineering is quite a hot topic
市面上的反汇编器有这几种情况
um and there are several state of our tools that have been developed
有些是贵得离谱的，有些是免费的
some of them are insanely expensive others are free
这些工具基本上是
um and these tools are basically
互动式的反汇编器
interactive disassemblers
他们允许逆向工程师坐下来
they allow a reverse engineer to sit down
然后深入研究一个程序来理解
and really dig into a program to um understand
慢慢地了解它是如何工作的
slowly build up understanding exactly how it works
不管是用来找bug还是
and whether it's for finding bugs or
或者理解如何与程序交互
or understanding how to interact with the program
或者其他
or whatever
这些都是静态工具
again these are static tools
其中一些支持一些动态特性
some of them support some dynamic features
但我们这里讨论的是它们的静态特性
but we're talking about their static features here
而且它们是在不运行程序的情况下
and they are made to without running a program
恢复一些（口误）
recovering some
了解程序是如何编写的
understanding of how that program was written
程序的目的是什么
why that program was written
程序逻辑是什么
and what the program logic is
好吧
all right
其中一些工具
some of these tools
首先是经典的
first the gold standard
在这些大型工具中最著名最古老的Ida Pro
kind of the best known the oldest one of these mega tools is Ida Pro
Ida全称 交互式反汇编程序
Ida stands for the Interact Interactive Disassembler
实际上是它创造了这个短语
so it actually kind of coined this phrase
它贵得离谱
it is absurdly expensive
除非你的生计依赖于它
unless your livelihood depends on it
那么这是一项必要且值得的投资
then you know it's a necessary and worthwhile investment
IDA的主要商业竞争对手是
Ida's main commercial competitor is
Binary Ninja 相对较新的产品
Binary Ninja relatively new product
起初叫 vector35
from the startup called vector 35
Binary Ninja 有个免费版本
and Binary Ninja has a free version
Binary Ninja Cloud 运行在你的浏览器
Binary Ninja Cloud that runs in your browser
这是我们在这门课上经常用到的
that's what we'll mostly be using in this class
它没有安装成本
it has no setup cost
你知道的，它非常好用
and it's you know very nice and and easy to use
还有很多开源软件
there are also a bunch of open source
反汇编和二进制分析框架
disassembling and and binary analysis framework
一个是angr management
one is angr management it's a
学术性的二进制分析框架，透露一下
academic binary analysis framework full disclosure
我是angr项目的联合创始人之一
uh I was one of the co founders of the Anger Project
直到今天，我还是这个项目的共同领导者之一
um and uh one of the the co leaders of it to this day
我们正在创建一个
uh so we are creating a
先进的有图形界面的二进制逆向工具
advanced binary reverse engineering tool that includes a graphical user interface
你可以去下载
that you can go download and
你知道的，帮助编写
and uh you know help write
修改代码
modified the code of of course
ghidra是一个
ghidra is a
国家安全局发明的逆向工具
reversing tool created by the National Security Agency
它最近已经开源了
open source recently it has
在开源之前，它已经被使用了很长一段时间，所以它是相当成熟的
been in use for for a very long time before it was open sourced and so it is quite mature
也非常强大
also very powerful
cutter是
and cutter is a
由开源Radar II项目创建的逆向工程工具
reverse engineering tool created by the open source Radar II project
市面上不缺乏先进的逆向工程工具
so there's no shortage of advanced reverse engineering tools
我们拿一个去看看
let's grab one and check it out on the
我之前摆弄过的cat
cat sample that I was messing around with earlier
好
alright
这是Binary Ninja的（口误）
this is Binary Ninjas
Binary Ninja cloud的web界面，我刚刚登录的
binary Ninja clouds web interface I just logged in
如果你访问cloud.binary.ninja
if you go to cloud.binary.ninja
您可以创建帐户
you can create an account
看到一些非常相似的东西
and see something very similar
可以选择新文件
can choose a new file
上传我的cat.elf
upload my cat.elf
继续
it continue
然后它
and it
会分析这个文件
will analyze this file
让它分析完
so let's let it finish analyzing
也许总是这样
maybe that's always
应该快分析完了
supposed to be there anyways
如果你还记得这个文件
so the file if you remember
它很简单
it's a very simple
等一下，猫的名字
hold up betray
请不要破坏东西
don't destroy things please
嗯
um
这是一个非常简单的文件
it's a very simple file
它有一个start函数会调用main然后
it has a start function that calls into main and then
调用exit
calls an exit call
然后如果你去看main函数
and then if you go to main
它主要是一个循环
it is a main function that basically just loops
直到
until
循环直到
that loops until
标准输入为空
standard input has nothing left to
然后它退出
give and then it exits
很简单
all right very simple
我为什么要给你们看这个
why am I showing you this
首先，看这些图表很有用
well one it's very useful to look at these graphs
我强烈推荐
I highly recommend
当你看这些图表的时候也可以
as you're looking at these graphs also turn on
用这个按钮
with this button here
打开地址显示，现在它展示了更多的信息
addresses so now this is even more information
如果你真的想
if you really want to be hip
您可以显示组成每条指令的字节码
you can show the op code bytes that make up each instruction
这些信息现在用不到
but this is just this is now too much information
好吧
well
除非你需要
unless you need that
好吧
alright
然后我
then I
我们该怎么用这个图呢，首先
what do we do with this graph, one it's
图更容易理解
it's easier to understand the graph
如果你不喜欢这个图
if you don't like the graph
你想要更接近
you want something closer to op （??）
你可以点击这个
you can click this
这是线性反汇编视图
this is the linear disassembly view
你也可以在这里显示地址
you can also show addresses here
好的，非常酷
okay very cool
否则
otherwise
当然我们也讲过字符串
also of course we talked about strings any
这个文件里没有字符串，但是你知道所有的
well there are no strings in this file but you know all
大多数这些反汇编程序都有字符串视图
most of these disassemblers also have a string view
有的视图可以看到程序使用了哪些变量类型等等
excuse me have a view where you can see what types are being used in the in the program and so forth
好吧
all right
通过这个程序图
this program graph
我们可以开始逆向这个程序
we can start reverse engineering this program
意味着可以提取信息
what does that mean that means extracting knowledge
通过看
by staring at
通过读这张图来理解它，但是
extracting knowledge by staring at this graph and understanding it but
Binary Ninja给我们提供了一些额外的工具
Binary Ninja gives us some additional tools
例如
for example
哦，等一下
oh hold on
例如，我们可以写注释
for example we can make comments
如果你
if you
右键点击这里，点击复制（口误，实际是注释）
right click here you can hit copy
你可以写注释
and you can write a comment
记下你当时在想什么
to kind of note down what you're thinking at the time
这里我认为这是一个函数序言
and here I'm thinking this is a function prologue
好吧，这很酷
okay that's very cool
现在我知道这是函数的序言
now I know this is a function prologue
我可以
I can
接着逆向这个。哦，好的，这我认识，这是
reverse engineer this I can see oh okay this is
个系统调用
this this call
把读到的数据放到栈上
calls read onto the stack
很好，这个系统调用我也认识
okay cool I can see this is call
好的，我们来注释一下
okay let's make a comment
我看了一下，它调用write
I'd I'd look over it and it calls write
写出之前读取的数据
calls write with the previously read data
好的，这里你可以看到
alright and here you see that
Binary Ninja 识别了一些变量
Binary Ninja identifies some variable
这个RSP叫var_108
so it says okay this RSP is variable 108
为什么是108
why is it 108
它是108，因为这是它相对于
it's 108 because that is where it's located relative to the
函数开始时的位置
stack position at the start of the function
因为我们把RBP入栈，占用了8个字节
because we pushed RBP that took up 8 bytes
然后从RSP中减去0x100
and then we subtracted 100 o x 100 from RSP
这里叫var 108只是因为
and this is now var 108 just based on its location
RSP现在指向的位置
where RSP is pointing to right now
相对于函数开始时它所指向的位置的差值
relative to where it was pointing to at the beginning of the function
这就是它如何命名变量的
that's how to identify variables
但我们也可以给它起个更好的名字
but we can also give it a better name
你可以看到这里
so you can see over here
Binary Ninja能够确定RSI
binary Ninja was able to determine that RSI
read的缓冲区
the buffer for read
和write的缓冲区是相同的变量
is the same variable as the buffer for write
这已经很有用了
so that's already quite useful
但是我们可以
but we can
给它起个更有描述性的名字，比如我们的缓冲区
name it something like a more descriptive like our buffer
或者
or
输入缓冲区，现在你可以
input buffer and now you can kind of see
一眼看出
at a glance a little bit more that
这个程序读入一个输入缓冲区
okay this program reads into an input buffer
然后把缓冲区中的内容写出来
and then write out of that buffer
现在我要给你们看一些神奇的东西
all right now I'm going to show you something magical
你可以点击这里
you can click here
你可以切换到所谓的high level IL
and you can switch to what is called high level IL
Binary Ninja会做一些分析
and binary Ninja will do a bunch of analysis
尽可能恢复成C代码
to try to recover something as close to C
这仍然是一个图形表示
this is still a graph representation
如果您点击listing并选择high level IL
if you click on the listing and select high level IL
然后几乎就有了源代码
then here you have almost source code
这有助于理解程序逻辑
this can be helpful in understanding program logic
它也可能存在些隐患
it can also be a little dangerous
因为它抽象了一些可能很重要的细节
because it abstracts some details that might be important
我建议
I recommend
为了本模块的目的，坚持使用汇编视图
for the purposes of this module sticking with the assembly view
理解汇编视图
and understanding the assembly view
好吧
alright
对于这个模块
for this module
这应该是您需要的工具
this should be the tools you need
用于静态分析的高级反汇编程序
a advanced disassembler for static analysis
一个先进的反汇编程序
an advanced disassembler with
内置了一些很棒的功能
some awesome built in capabilities
binary Ninja 将所有这些自动保存在云端
binary Ninja saves all of this automatically in the cloud
当然，您可以有多个会话
you can of course have multiple sessions
你可以尝试其他功能
you can play around with other crazy stuff
比如把图嵌入到图中
like embedding the graph within a graph or whatever
不管怎样，这里有一些疯狂的功能
anyways there's crazy features here
你可以随便玩，但是
that you can play around with but
当然，最主要的优势
the main advantage of this of course
它能在浏览器中运行
is that it runs in your browser
没有什么需要你安装的
there's nothing for you to install
你可以像这样开始逆向工程
you can just start reverse engineering just like that
下集我们会讲到
in the next video we'll go on to
学习如何
learning how to
动态调试分析进程
kind of poke up program as it as it's doing stuff
感谢收看
thanks for watching